<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on the 16th day of April 1696 in the parish church of St. Michael in New-Malton, being the thanksgiving day appointed for the discovery and disappointment of the horrible and barbarous conspiracy &amp;c. / by William Perse.</title>
            <author>Perse, William, 1640 or 41-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09124451</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09124451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1314:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on the 16th day of April 1696 in the parish church of St. Michael in New-Malton, being the thanksgiving day appointed for the discovery and disappointment of the horrible and barbarous conspiracy &amp;c. / by William Perse.</title>
                  <author>Perse, William, 1640 or 41-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes X, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>On the 16th Day of</hi> April, 1696.</p>
            <p>In the Pariſh Church of <hi>St.</hi> Michael <hi>in</hi> New-Malton: BEING THE Thankſgiving Day Appointed for the Diſcovery and Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Horrible and Barbarous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Perſe, <hi>M. A. Miniſter of</hi> Malton, <hi>and formerly</hi> Fellow <hi>of</hi> King's College <hi>in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationer's-Hall,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42478:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42478:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable The Lady PALMS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R favourable Acceptance of that ſmall Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will Offering that I paid to the Memory of the Beſt of Women, our late moſt Gracious Queen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages me to hope that your wonted Goodneſs, which I have long experienc'd, will vouchſafe to receive this mean Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtical Oblation for the Deliverance of our Dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, (the Beſt of Princes) from the Barbarous and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Conſpiracy, that was laid againſt His Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Government, with the ſame Candor which you did the Former: Eſpecially ſince in Obedience to your Honour's Commands, which I ſhall ever to the utmoſt of my Power with all readineſs obſerve, it is made thus Publick. And I am the rather induced to ſuffer it to paſs through more hands than it was at firſt deſigned for, becauſe the Chief Subject it treats of, (being the Peculiar and extraordinary Providence, which watches over Good and Righteous Kings, for the Security and Protection of themſelves and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt the moſt Secret Contrivances that can be form'd againſt them) may, I hope, convince every one of the Folly and Vanity, as well as Sinfulneſs and Danger, of all ſuch attempts that are made againſt either: And that this Particular inſtance of the Wonderful Diſcovery of the late Bloudy and Treacherous Deſign, that was ſo deeply laid
<pb facs="tcp:42478:3"/>againſt the Life of our Gracious Prince, joyned to that ſeries of Signal Providences which hath all along attended his Royal Perſon for his Preſervation from all thoſe Perils to which he hath been ſo frequently expoſed, may at length cauſe that Obſtinate Party, which hath hitherto ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably ſtood out, to comply with, and to own that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which GOD hath ſo viſibly and ſo ſignally appeared for; and by which their own Liberties and Religion, have continued ſafe to them, and us.</p>
            <p>That our Church, (the Beſt and Pureſt of all other) and our State, may long Flouriſh under the Happy and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reign of our Wiſe, Valiant, Merciful, and Religious Leader whom God's own Right-hand hath placed over us, and made ſo ſtrong for himſelf; And that your Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Family, which hath ſo Zealouſly eſpouſed the Intereſts of both, may always enjoy the Bleſſings that accrue to this Nation thereby, and the Everlaſting Happineſs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that is above afterwards, is, the earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honour's Moſt Faithful, and Obedient Servant, <hi>William Perſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42478:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SERMON</hi> Preach'd on the <hi>16th</hi> of <hi>April, 1696.</hi> being the Thanksgiving-Day.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, Chap. 10. Ver. 20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Curſe not the King, no not in thy Thought, and Curſe not the Rich, no not in thy Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is a general Providence, that to any obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eye, is viſible over the face of the whole Creation, whereby all things are kept, and preſerved in their own Order, and Way of ſubſiſting, by the ſame Divine Power which at firſt formed, and brought them into Being: and according to the ſeveral Degrees of Perfection of thoſe divers Species which God Created, (for when he ſaw every thing that he had made, behold it was very good) hath he proportioned the manner, and the meaſure of their preſervation. Though nothing, no not of the moſt minute conſequence can paſs without his Knowledge, and which is not under his Eye, yet Creatures of the loweſt rank, and ſize, cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to claim ſo great a ſhare of his Protection, for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42478:4"/>their continuance in that ſtation wherein Nature hath placed them, as thoſe which are of a more eminent, and uſeful Quality in the World. And as Infects which are of an equivocal Generation, ſome of which are but of a days duration, come into the World by Shoals, ſo they tumble out of it again by heaps. Thus the Locuſts, God's great Army, as they are called in the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> which covered the face of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as they were brought in on a ſuddain by an <hi>Eaſt</hi> Wind; ſo after they had conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all the Forage in the Land, and done the Work which God had appointed them, a mighty <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind caſt them back again, as ſuddainly into the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. But as the ſcale of the Creature riſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes more ſerviceable to that great End for which he Created all things, <hi>viz.</hi> Man's Happineſs, and his own Glory; ſo hath he ordered all means to concur ſuitably for their conducing in their proper ways towards the promoting of that Deſign, to which every thing in its reſpective capacity is, and muſt be ſubſervient. And this our Bleſſed Saviour plainly intimates to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, in his Diſcourſe concerning Providence; wherein he tells them, that God preſerves the Graſs which is to day in the Field, and to morrow in the Oven; and that he ordereth Food for the Ravens, that have neither Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe nor Barn; and that not one Sparrow is forgotten before him: inferring from thence by an Argument drawn <hi>a fortiori</hi> from the ſtronger ſide, that they ought in their greateſt Exigencies, and Extremities, to depend upon God's Care of them, and his Love towards them; ſeeing, if he does not neglect his Creatures of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Degree, but ſuſtains them in a way ſuitable to their own Nature; it muſt needs follow that he will take a more particular Care of thoſe whom he hath made after his own Image, and for whoſe ſake chiefly, all his other Works in this lower World were Created, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42478:4"/>to their uſe, and ſervice; and that he will let them lack nothing that may tend, not only to the continuance of their Being, but their Well-being alſo: And as I have drawn this Scheme of Providence from its loweſt Baſis, till we come to the higheſt Spire, and top of this ſublunary World; all whoſe parts mutually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon one another; and which are all conſerv'd by the ſame All powerful Hand from which they receiv'd their Original; ſo the Beauty, and Harmony, of this wonderful, and ſtupendous Frame will more eminently and conſpicuouſly appear, and the infinite Wiſdom of the Almighty Architect be the more viſible, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that even in the diſpenſation of his great Care and Providence over Man himſelf, the Nobleſt and finiſht Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterpiece of his Six Days Works, that even here, as to Perſons of the ſame kind, he puts a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, in order to their particular ſecurity, and preſervation, according as they are by his Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, to be more or leſs concern'd in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of that Government, which he hath conſtituted for the eſtabliſhing theſe things, in that Order wherein he firſt placed them; and without which they would run into Anarchy, and Confuſion: and therefore, althô for the better preſervation of Mankind, he hath denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a ſevere penalty againſt every one, who ſhould up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any unwarrantable Account Deſtroy the Life of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; Declaring, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould ſhed Man's Blood, by Man his Bloud ſhould be ſhed:</hi> yet he hath thought fit to lay a particular Injunction upon all Perſons, not to offer any violence to thoſe whom he (for by him Kings Reign) hath ſet in Authority over his People; to which end he hath fixed a peculiar Mark, and Character upon thoſe whom he hath deſign'd, and appointed for publick Offices of Truſt; upon whoſe welfare the ſafety of the whole depends, to keep their Perſons Sacred, and Invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42478:5"/>ſaying, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, and do my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets no harm:</hi> becauſe by them he was to promulgate, and put in execution thoſe Laws and Precepts, which if duely obſerved, would keep the World in Peace, and Proſperity here, and lead them the way to Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs hereafter; And likewiſe to be a Terror to thoſe who would not yield Obedience to his Commands: for the Magiſtrate is not only the Miniſter of God, for the incouragement of them that do well, but likewiſe a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger to execute Wrath upon him who doth evil. <hi>Touch not God's Anointed, no, not with the venemous Arrow of thy Tongue:</hi> for he hath given a particular Charge, that none ſhould dare to Curſe the Ruler of his People; as it is Recorded, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. To which St. <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes in the 23 of the <hi>Acts, ver</hi> 5. when he was taxed for reviling the High Prieſt; when he ſays, <hi>I wiſt not Brethren that he was the High Prieſt, for it is written, thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy People;</hi> and it was no leſs then death to do ſo; as appears by what <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſaid concerning the Railer <hi>Shimei; Shall not Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei be put to death for this, becauſe he curſed the Lord's Anointed?</hi> And <hi>David,</hi> when he dying, left it in Charge to his Son, <hi>Not to hold him guiltleſs, but to bring down his Hoar-Head to the Grave with Blood;</hi> and we find that he was afterwards ſlain upon that old ſcore, by <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Commandment. But here my Text ſeems to go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when the ſame Wiſe Man tells us, That we muſt not only forbear from caſting Reproaches, and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies upon our Governor, by ſcurrilous and opprobrious Language, thereby to make him vile, and to blacken him in the Eyes and Eſteem of his Subjects, to the endangering his Perſon and his Government; but we muſt not ſo much as in the ſecret of our Heart, think evil of him, nor wiſh his ill; nor in our mind, contrive to do him any Miſchief, for even that Thought of the Heart, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42478:5"/>was the firſt mover of the wicked Deſign, (for as our Saviour ſays, <hi>Out of the Heart proceed Murders, faiſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Blaſphemies,</hi> &amp;c.) ſhall not go undiſcovered, before it come to its full execution, and conſequently, ſhall not be unpuniſht.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curſe not the King, no, not in thy Thought</hi> (ſays the wiſeſt of Princes) <hi>nor the Rich, no not in thy Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Solomon,</hi> to whom God had given a Wiſe, and Underſtanding Heart, had ſearched narrowly into the Cauſes of all things under the Sun, and ſtrictly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, as you will find throughout this whole Book of his Sermons; all the Proceedings of God in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Affairs of this World, ſo far forth as they were knowable and apprehenſible by their effects; and does more particularly inſiſt upon the various methods of his Providential Diſpenſations towards his Creatures, than upon any other Subject whatſoever. And upon a general Survey, he acquaints us, that he had obſerved, that as God had not placed all things on a Level, ſo neither had he left all things to be guided and order'd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily by the common Rules of Nature, which he hath preſcribed to the whole Creation; but that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, whenever he pleaſes, he interpoſes his own Power, for the bringing about his own Ends, to the fruſtrating of thoſe Deſigns, which, had they been left to work ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtrength and vigour of thoſe proper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and means whereby they were acted and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, muſt have produced effects ſuitable to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Cauſes: Thus he tells us, <hi>that the Race is not always to the Swift, nor yet the Battle to the Strong, nor Bread to the Wiſe, nor Riches to Men of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;</hi> though theſe in their ſeveral ways, are the beſt qualifications for the obtaining of thoſe Ends: And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42478:6"/>as God hath put a great difference between thoſe of the ſame kind, ordaining ſome to Rule, and others to obey, by which ſubordination the Government of the World is preſerved in that uniform Harmony wherein it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues as to the main, at this day; ſo does he take a more particular Care of thoſe whom he hath appointed for the adminiſtration of Juſtice, and the preſervation of the Rights and Liberties of his People, committed to their Charge, then of others of the ordinary ſort, and mould; as knowing, that they would be apt to be expoſed to a thouſand hazards, and violences for the due execution of their Office; it being a difficult matter to ſatisfie and pleaſe all Parties that ſue to them for Juſtice, and to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie all thoſe who pretend by extraordinary Services to have merited great Favours from their Prince; and then, the Party who thinks himſelf wrong'd and aggriev'd for want of ſuch a favourable Sentence as he expected in his Cauſe; or, who thinks he is not ſufficiently rewarded according to his Deſerts, will be prone to Meditate and Study Revenge, and to ſide with thoſe who are diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the ſame, or any other Account: And therefore the All Wiſe Moderator of the World hath thought fit, in order to the keeping the frame of Government on the Wheels, and to prevent that diſturbance that would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to the Publick by the frequent Change, and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Magiſtrates; and to encourage Perſons qualify'd thereunto, to take thoſe weighty and troubleſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments upon them, to ſecure and protect them with a higher, and more defenſible Mound and Bulwark of his ſpecial Providence then ordinary, and to ſet a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Watch over them; ſo that there cannot be ſo much as the leaſt Thought of evil deſigned againſt them; nor the cloſeſt contrivance hatcht in the moſt ſecret Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Heart, either againſt their Perſons, or their Government (ſo long as they are approved by him, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42478:6"/>that they act in conformity to thoſe great and good Ends for which he ſet them in thoſe places of Truſt, as well as Honour) but as it is known to him from whom nothing is hid, ſo doth he in his own time, when he ſees all things ripe for execution, ſend his Emiſſaries, and diſpatch his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to diſcover the bottom of thoſe damnable and helliſh Conſpiracies that are plotted againſt them, and thereby to fruſtrate, and defeat their deepeſt, and moſt ſecret Deſigns; for there is nothing of this kind ſo hid, but ſhall be made manifeſt; That which they have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Darkneſs, ſhall be heard in the Light, and that which they have whisper'd in the Ear, in Cloſets, ſhall be proclaimed upon the Houſe tops; <hi>For a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the Voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which expreſſions does appear the wonderful and extraordinary Care, that God Almighty the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords does take of Kings, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates that he hath ſet in Authority over us; for by Birds of the Air in this place, and thoſe that have Wings, we may ſafely conclude to be meant the Holy Angels, thoſe winged Meſſengers of Heaven, thoſe Miniſtring Spirits which he ſends abroad upon all emergent Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, for the good of his Elect; and eſpecially for the preſervation of thoſe whom he hath mark'd and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd with more than ordinary Beams of his own Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and Glory. He hath certainly given his Angels a particular Charge over thoſe good Princes who execute Judgment and Righteouſneſs, and who make it their buſineſs to preſerve the Peace, and Proſperity of all thoſe whom the Divine Wiſdom hath committed to their Care, and Protection: And that there are Tutelar An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels preſiding over Kings, and their Kingdoms is plain from the Tenth Chapter of <hi>Daniel</hi> in ſeveral parts of it; and as they are ſet by God for a Guard over his Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42478:7"/>ſo are they ſent likewiſe for the deliverance of his Prophets alſo; thus God ſent his Angel, as you find in the <hi>12th Chap.</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and deliver'd <hi>Peter</hi> out of the hand of <hi>Herod,</hi> and from all the expectation of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Jews:</hi> and that it was the Opinion of his Friends that he had a peculiar Angel attending on him for his ſafety, appears in that after the Maid affirmed conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he was knocking at the Door, and they could not be brought to believe a thing which they thought upon a ſurprize impoſſible, they ſaid, <hi>It is his Angel.</hi> And though ſometimes God ſuffer a Pious, and Religious Prince, for the ſins of a Nation, whom he deſigns, either to chaſtize for their amendment, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy for their Obſtinacy, and Ingratitude; to fall into the Ambuſhes, and to be taken in the Nets of wicked and Blood-thirſty Men; yet in the general courſe of his Providence, he does uſually by ſome ſignal means, or other ſhow his great Care of them, by delivering them contrary to the expectation of their Enemies, from all the open force that is gathered, and from all the hidden Treachery that is contriv'd, and manag'd againſt them; by diſcovering the Deſigns that are form'd againſt their Perſons, and their Government, by theſe ſpeedy and ſwift Meſſengers whom he imploys for that very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Neither are thoſe Heavenly Spirits which continually wait about the Throne of God, and are always ready to obey his Will, and to diſpatch his Commands, unfitly by the Wiſe Man likened unto the Birds of the Air, to thoſe ſwift Creatures that have Wings wherewith they are able to meaſure vaſt diſtances of ſpace in a Short time, and to Protect and Preſerve whatſoever they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and receive under the Shadow and Coverture of them. The Repreſentation of the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> the higheſt Order in the Caeleſtial Hierarchy, was made by God's
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42478:7"/>own appointment by Creatures with Wings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they covered they covered the Mercy-Seat; and in all the Viſions of the Prophets, they always appeared to them in that form; and the <hi>Seraphim</hi> that was ſent to the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is ſaid to fly unto him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. v. 6. Nothing ſo ſwift to convey Intelligence as thoſe winged Poſts of the Air, to which purpoſe Doves we know are frequently made uſe of, to be News Carriers in the Eaſtern Parts of the World to this day; and therefore nothing ſo proper to repreſent the Activity and Celerity of thoſe Faithful Meſſengers which God diſpatches in the time of Danger, to warn his Vice-gerents of thoſe Wicked Deſigns that are formed againſt them, and to diſcover by thoſe Ways and Methods he orders, thoſe hidden practices that the Devil and his Agents are plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Contriving againſt them; and think that no Eye can ſee them, and that it is beyond the Art of Man, as ſometimes indeed without the Hand of God it is, to hinder the Execution of them. Theſe are the true Birds of Paradiſe, which have Wings and no Feet: Wings to expreſs their Swiftneſs wherewith they haſte to give tidings either of Good or Evil, to thoſe to whom they are directed by their great Lord and Maſter; but no Feet to fix upon any Earthly Object, or to make any ſtay there. Though indeed, no Creature on this ſide Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven can in any due proportion, repreſent the wonderful Agility of thoſe Spiritual Subſtances, who move quicker than Thought it ſelf, whereby they communicate the Will of GOD to thoſe to whom they are ſent: Nor yet can we tell the Secret ways whereby they inſtill and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate thoſe early Notices into their Breaſts, to forewarn them of the Dangers wherewith they are threatned. Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent it is, that we know they attend for that very end; and that we have Scripture, and frequent Experience for the Confirmation and Avouchment of it. Theſe are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42478:8"/>the Heavenly Intelligencers that belong to the Court a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, which upon all Emergent Occaſions, fly on the Wings of the Wind by their ſecret Intimations to bring to nought the moſt hidden Counſels of the Wicked, and to make all theſe Devices, though never ſo artificially laid, againſt thoſe Publick Perſons who are the more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate care of Heaven, of none effect. And how, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſhould it be otherwiſe, when, as my Text aſſures us, that the leaſt Malicious Curſe, and Evil Intention, that is lodg'd in the cloſeſt Caverns of the Heart againſt Kings, and Publick Magiſtrates, (for by rich Men are meant here Magiſtrates, becauſe they are taken and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from out of that rank which is moſt eminent for Wealth and Honour) ſhall not be undiſcover'd. So that the Wiſe Man here ſhews the Vanity and Folly of all thoſe wretched Miſcreants who conſpire and lay their heads together, to overthrow the Foundations of that Government which God's Providence hath ſetled; by the Deſtruction of the Heads and Supporters of it. Seeing, as he tells us, that not the leaſt Deſign of Harm that is contrived againſt their Perſons, though it be never ſo deep laid, never ſo cloſely managed in the moſt private Bed-Chamber, but as it is known to him, who ſearcheth the Secrets of the Heart, to whom Darkneſs and Light are both alike, ſo when the curſed Deſign ſhall by the untimely Diſcovery of it miſcarry, and become abortive, it brings not only Shame, but Puniſhment alſo to the Raſh and Deſperate Undertakers.</p>
            <p>God by his Holy Spirit, or the Miniſtry of his Angels, ſometimes lays open the Secret Counſels and Machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are intended againſt his Choſen ones to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and by ſome ſudden, and almoſt unaccountable impulſe of Spirit, they are prompted to ſuch thoughts that tend to the Preventing and Diſappointing the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy that is laid againſt them: Thus God put it into
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42478:8"/>the Heart of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, to unriddle that My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Letter, by which Interpretation, that Horrible and Helliſh Powder-plot of the Papiſts which was near its Execution was prevented. Sometimes God raiſes good to a Prince and his Government, from the Evil that was intended againſt it; making the breaking-forth of the Treaſon inſtrumental to the Settlement and Security of thoſe, whoſe Ruine and Deſtruction was thereby malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly endeavoured and deſign'd. Thus after <hi>Abner</hi> the General of the Army, had ſet up <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> the Son and Heir of <hi>Saul,</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> whom God had choſen to be King, though he was not of the Royal Line; and was defeated, and diſappointed of his great Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> ever after, as may be ſeen in the Second Book of <hi>Samuel, c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1. waxed ſtronger and ſtronger, and the Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> weaker and weaker from that very day. And when <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Treaſon was diſcover'd and brought to nothing, it made abundantly for the Peace of <hi>David</hi> all his Reign after. It ſettled the Hearts of the Twelve Tribes, which were in part divided, wholly towards him; ſo that they all then una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly Aſſociated, and friendly ſtrove togther who ſhould have the greateſt ſhare in him, and do the moſt for him. Sometimes God, for the Preſervation of the Perſon whom he intruſts with the Government, inſpires the Hearts of his Prophets with the Knowledge of the Secret Counſels of thoſe that riſe up againſt them, and thereby eludes and diſappoints the Succeſs of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. Thus when the King of <hi>Syria</hi> warr'd againſt <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> he took Counſel with his Servants, ſaying, in ſuch and ſuch a Place ſhall be my Camp: The Man of God immediately ſent to the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to beware of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to that place, for thither, ſaith he, the <hi>Syrians</hi> are come down, and he ſaved himſelf, as the Text ſays, not once, nor twice that way: Therefore the King of <hi>Syria</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42478:9"/>was troubled, and concluded that ſome of his own Privy Council had betray'd his Secrets; till one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants told him, that none but the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> had revealed his moſt ſecret Intentions, for ſaith he, he tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Words that thou ſpeakeſt in thy Bed-Chamber.</p>
            <p>You ſee then, that God is pleas'd in a more Peculiar manner to take upon himſelf the Care and Protection of his Anointed, and to appear in ſundry manners for the Diſcovery of thoſe hidden Counſels that are hatch'd in the moſt Secret Places againſt them. And this God does, as I have already hinted, for the continuance of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Government of the World, which would in every ſhort Period of time be put out of Joynt, if the Deſigns of Proud, Ambitious, and Revengeful Men, who upon ſeveral Intereſts are ready at every turn to combine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that are poſſeſs'd of the Seat of Honour, and the Throne of Juſtice, ſhould obtain their deſign'd and intended Effect. For the Welfare and Proſperity of the People, are lock'd and treaſur'd up in the Life and Safety of a Good, Virtuous, Valiant, and Couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince; whoſe Life, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> told King <hi>David,</hi> as truly, as well as affectionately, in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Publick Good, is worth ten thouſand of his Subjects: Seeing their loſs may eaſily be recruited and made up again; but the loſs of a good King is ſo much the greater, by how much the harder to be repaired again. Beſides, the diſmal conſequences that attend a Nation ween depriv'd ſuddainly, accidentally, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly of him, on whoſe ſtaffe of Authority, under GOD, their Strength chiefly depended, and relyed, makes the Caſe moſt deplorable. The Prophet <hi>Zachariah</hi> took two Staves, the one he called <hi>Beauty,</hi> the other <hi>Bands,</hi> when thoſe Two were broken, and Three Shepheards cut off in one Month; the Order of the Government
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42478:9"/>wherein conſiſted its Beauty, and its Bands, wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted its ſtrength, was diſſolved; and the Brotherhood between <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> was broken: as you may ſee, <hi>Zachariah</hi> 11.7, <hi>to the 14th.</hi> upon this account God, (ſome particular Caſes only reſerv'd) does uſually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thoſe good Princes whom he raiſes up, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to the Peace and Proſperity of his People, as he does the Earth it ſelf, with a Shield; and protects them both from the open Aſſaults, and the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hidden Plots, and Conſpiracies of their moſt furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and implacable Enemies.</p>
            <p>Why then do theſe worſe then heathen Miſcreants, from time to time conſpire againſt the Lives of Princes, and take Council together againſt the Lord, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed; ſaying, <hi>Let us break their bands, even the bands of their Lives aſunder, and caſt their cords from us: Why do they rage ſo furiouſly, and imagine ſuch a vain thing; and contrive ſuch deſigns as they are not able to perform? For he that ſitteth on high ſhall laugh them to ſcorn, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion, when they leaſt think of it, he ſhall ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure; he ſhall break them with a rod of Iron, and daſh them in pieces like a Potters veſſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely the reaſon why theſe miſchievous workers of Iniquity in ſecret Places, who lay in wait for Blood, and lurk privily in corners for the Innocent, without a cauſe, are ſo bent upon theſe wicked and abominable Deſigns, is their miſapprehenſion of the Divine Nature: They do not certainly believe that God takes any notice of what is done, and acted in this Lower World, but imagine that he ſits an unconcern'd Spectator of the various Scenes that are preſented on the Theatre of the Earth; and that he lets every thing go on, and ſucceed ſuitably to the Vigour and Energy of thoſe Natural Cauſes, by which it is managed, without any interpoſition of his own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42478:10"/>Power to controul, and check their Proceedings, though he never ſo much diſlike, and diſapprove of them: or elſe they fondly conceive, that their hidden Deeds of Darkneſs are unknown to him, and that he cannot pierce into the depth of their ſecret Councels; otherwiſe, did they either believe that God took any particular Care of the Government of the World; or that he was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerner of the Thoughts, and Intents of the Heart; they would not be ſo fooliſhly impudent as to dare to Plot againſt the Lives, and to deviſe and compaſs the death of thoſe whom he hath more peculiarly ſhrowded under the wings of his particular, and eſpecial Providence. This is the very Reaſon given by the Royal Prophet, why theſe workers of Iniquity boaſt themſelves in their Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.4.7. They ſay, <hi>the Lord ſhall not ſee, neither the God of Jacob regard it:</hi> But he preſently convinces them of their Folly and Ignorance, in the next Verſe; when he ſays, <hi>Ye fools, when will ye be wiſe? He that planted the Ear, ſhall he not hear? He that formed the Eye, ſhall he not ſee?</hi> Yea, he ſees them in their moſt private Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, and in their moſt ſecret Conſultations, and lets them alone till they fancy they have brought their bloudy Deſigns beyond any poſſibility of diſappointment. He knows their Down-ſittings, and their Up-riſings; he is about their Path, and about their Bed, and ſpieth out all their ways; yea, there is not a word in their Tongue but he knoweth it altogether; nay, he underſtandeth their Thoughts, from whence proceed all their evil Deeds, long before; when they are yet a far off; for the Thought is the main Spring, and Original of all Humane Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Heart is that ſmall ſpot, that little dark Cloud which, though not ſo big as a Mans Hand, would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch ſhowers of Bloud, if not prevented by Divine Providence, as would overflow whole Countries. Here the wicked Traitor, after he hath conceived miſchief, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velleth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42478:10"/>with Iniquity, and bringeth forth Falſhood. Here Ambition and Revenge, when they have conceiv'd ſome cunning ſtratagem for the accompliſhing their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Deſign, bring forth their monſtrous and deformed Iſſue of Sin, and that Sin bringeth forth Death, either to the Author, or the Parties againſt whom the Plot is contrived; but moſt commonly the miſchief returns upon their own Head; and their violent dealing comes down with a vengeance on their own Pates: For thô the Anvil of the Heart, upon which all their ungodly Projects are hammer'd, be never ſo ſoft quilted, that the boldeſt ſtrokes whereby they are forging miſchief againſt the Lords Anointed, and againſt his Church, cannot be heard by the quickeſt Ear; yet even the leaſt Thought doth not ſcape his knowledge, from whom nothing is hid; though for a while he lets them go on in their Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, till at length he taketh them in their own crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and their Counſels come down headlong upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Thus the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays particularly to this Point, when Treaſon was hatch'd againſt his own Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>Pſal</hi> 37.12, <hi>&amp;c. The wicked plotteth againſt the Juſt, and gnaſheth upon him with his Teeth; The Lord ſhall taugh him to ſcorn, for he ſeeth that his day is coming; the wicked have drawn their Sword, and bent their Bow</hi> (all inſtruments of Cruelty ready for the fatal execution) <hi>to caſt down the poor and needy, and to ſlay ſuch as are of an upright Converſation; But,</hi> behold the iſſue; <hi>their Sword ſhall enter into their own Heart, and their Bow ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The wicked watcheth the righteous and ſeeketh to ſlay him; but the Lord will not leave him in his hand, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him when he is judged; the Righteous ſhall rejoyce when he ſeeth the vengeance, and ſhall waſh his footſteps in the bloud of the wicked;</hi> ſo that a Man ſhall ſay, <hi>Verily, there is a reward for the Righteous, doubtleſs, there is a God that judgeth the Earth.</hi> Pſal. 58.10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42478:11"/>
And this inſenſibly leads me to that which is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Proof of what the Wiſe Man lays down in my Text: an Undeniable Inſtance and Demonſtration, of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Care that God takes of thoſe Good and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princes, into whoſe hands he hath committed the Reins of Government, for the Eſtabliſhing of the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Proſperity of his People; manifeſted in the late Signal and Wonderful Act of his good Providence, in diſcovering the late Barbarous and Inhumane Conſpiracy againſt the Precious Life of our Dear and Dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, in whom all our Lives and Welfares are wrapt up: Which ſhews the Watchful Eye that the Almighty hath over his Royal Perſon, which he hath ſo often ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, not only from the Caſualties of War, which have been many and great, but from the ſecret Plots and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of Deceitful, and Blood-Thirſty-Men, which have been formed and contrived againſt him; for this is not the firſt time that they have laid wait privily to deſtroy him, nor the firſt Demonſtration of God's won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Deliverance of him. O who can ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abhor the Villanous Attempt of thoſe Barbarous and Bloudy Aſſaſſins, againſt the Sacred Life of our moſt Gracious Prince, or enough praiſe the Almighty's Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the Preſervation of it? Who can without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and amazement of Spirit conſider what the diſmal and fatal Conſequences would have been to this Land and Nation wherein we Live, if God, for the Sins of this ungrateful People, had ſuffer'd this Black and Helliſh Conſpiracy hatcht in the Secrets of Darkneſs to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the expected Succeſs. Had the Breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord, under whoſe ſhadow we hope long to be ſhelter'd from the Fury of all our Popiſh Enemies, been taken in their Nets, what a ſad Confuſion would there have been among all Orders, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and Conditions of Men among us? What Rivers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42478:11"/>of Blood would have run in lately dry places; when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man's hand had been againſt his Neighbour? What Murders, what Out-crys, what Groans, and Shrieks of Dying Perſons? What Devaſtations by Fire, to conſume that beautiful and magnificent City, one of the Europae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Wonders, which hath riſen more glorious out of thoſe Aſhes in which thoſe implacable Incendiaries had not long ſince laid it. And all this to be follow'd (for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the accompliſhing the Barbarous Aſſaſſination, it would have been in vain to attempt it) by a terrible and formidable Invaſion, when all things were in hurry and Diſorder; and a ſudden Fear and Aſtoniſhment for the diſmal and unexpected Blow had ſeized upon the hearts of all good Men; and no Preparations at hand to have reſiſted the vaſt Numbers of Armed and Well-Diſciplin'd Men, which would continually have been pouring forth upon us: And all this to bring us into Slavery and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, to a Cruel and Perfidious Nation that hates us, and which we have no other Reaſon but only as Enemies, to Love; and what is worſe yet, to deſtroy our Rights and Liberties, and that which ought to be deareſt to us, to extirpate our moſt holy Religion, and to introduce the Hateful Names of Popery and Tyranny among us. And how near was all this dire Miſchief to be accompliſh'd? Juſt upon the Edge of Execution: The black Cloud that hung over our Heads, that was charged with Thunder and Lightning, was ready to break down upon us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he who is higher than they, had diverted the Bloody and Dreadful Storm. For God was pleaſed to diſcover this Horrid and Deteſtable Conſpiracy but a day before the Fatal time intended for the accompliſhment of it. He touch'd the Heart of one of the Conſpirators by a ſudden Impulſe of his Spirit, with a Remorſe for that Barbarous and Inhumane Deſign wherein he had engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, and made him ſee with Horror and Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42478:12"/>of Mind, the Blackneſs and Unworthineſs of that Cowardly and ungenerous Fact he was about to commit: So that he could not be at quiet, nor take any reſt, till he had vomitted up, and diſgorged the Bloody Secret which he had ſo greedily ſwallow'd. God making him, and others that were pick'd out to be of the Party to Aſſaſſinate our Gracious Prince, (and they were more than Forty, the like number of thoſe who had banded together to kill St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who made this Conſpiracy) to be the happy Inſtruments of his wonderful Deliverance and Preſervation. Thus God, when he pleaſes to appear for the ſafety of the Church and his People, can turn a Lion into a Lamb; he can make of <hi>Saul,</hi> who was a Perſecutor of the Saints, a <hi>Paul,</hi> a Preacher, and an Apoſtle, and a Propagator of his Holy Goſpel. Thus near was this Deadly, Execrable Plot of being fully executed upon us: And that there was ſomething at that very time extraordinary in the Wind, ſome great matter hoped, and ſuddenly look'd for by that Party, which is ſtill, though God be praiſed for it, unſucceſsfully plotting the Downful both of our Church and State, might eaſily have been conjectur'd, (neither did it miſs the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome) by the more than ordinary Feaſting and Revelling, and meeting together of the profeſſed Enemies of our Religion; the Flocking together of thoſe ill-boding Vultures in unuſual numbers of that time in the chiefeſt Places of concourſe, ſhewed that they more than ſmelt the Bloody Deſign; and that they were in daily expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their long-look'd for Prey; waiting to be gorged with Royal Blood; and that with the Gore of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Sacrifices of both the Senatorian Orders, as well as of thoſe of inferior Ranks which muſt have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctly fallen, to have made way for the compleating of that deteſtable, and almoſt unparallel'd deſign which they had undertaken. And indeed, the time of extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42478:12"/>of Danger is the uſual Seaſon that God for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his own Honour, and to ſhew that it is his Hand that does it, chuſes for the Diſcovering and Fruſtrating the Wicked Counſels of thoſe who are in deep Conſult, to overthrow the Foundations of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment he hath eſtabliſh'd, and for the Deliverance of his Choſen Servants: When the Mandatory-Letters were ſent Poſt by <hi>Haman</hi>'s Order to deſtroy, to kill, and cauſe to Periſh the whole Nation of the Jews, then was God pleaſed to give <hi>Eſther</hi> ſo much favour in the ſight of the King, as to obtain to have them coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-manded, and to turn the Deſtruction intended againſt them upon the Heads of the Authors themſelves: O may we ever, as the Jews did, keep ſolemn the two days of our <hi>Purim,</hi> for our wonderful Deliverance, when the Lot was on both days caſt to conſume, and deſtroy us; That theſe Days may be may kept Holy to the Lord by an Ordinance, according to their appointed time every Year, that they may be remember'd in every Generation, and the Memorial of them be continued to our Poſterity after us. Again, when the Match was laid to the Train, and the Conſpirators were in expectation every Minute to hear the Fatal Crack, then GOD, when they leaſt expected it, was pleas'd to open the long hidden Mine, and to diſcover their Magazine of Ammunition that was laid to have blown up the King, with all the Flower of his Nobility and Gentry, together with our Religion, at one blaſt. Thus God ſuffer'd this damnable Conſpiracy for the greater Confuſion of the Traytors, who fell ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly from their hopes with which they were puff'd up; and to give us the greater occaſion to Praiſe and Magnifie his Goodneſs towards us, to come juſt to the Birth, and then would not give it ſtrength to come forth. He ſaw them all along; follow'd them from one place of Meeting to another, his Eye purſued them from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42478:13"/>one Tavern to another; for there in thoſe Temples, Dedicated to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> they held their moſt Private and nocturnal Conſults; there, on his ſlippery Altars they ſacrific'd their Drink-offerings in intemperate Bowles, for the ſucceſs of their unhallow'd, and moſt bloody Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and when they were thorowly heated with the furious Spirit of their impure Deity, then were they fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to contrive, and the moſt audacious to execute the maddeſt, and moſt deſperate Deſigns: <hi>Dignum ſanè Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellâ operculum;</hi> a fit Cover for ſuch a Meſs; A proper Place, and fit Ingredients for the carrying on ſuch a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and bloody Enterprize, that no Man in his right Wits, and in a ſober Mind, durſt ſo much as think on. Thus <hi>Cataline,</hi> ſuch another bold Conſpirator againſt his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as theſe were; who plotted the Death of one of the Chief Magiſtrates, <hi>Tully,</hi> the beſt Conſul, they almoſt ever had; and the burning the City; the ſlaughter of the Senate, and the ruin of their Temples, and all that was Sacred among them, (juſt ſuch another Holy and Worthy Project as this was) kept all his debauched Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults by night, with all manner of lewd Intemperance, and Exceſs; and when they were high flown, then he carried about a great Goblet, wherein Wine and Man's Blood was mix'd together; and when all his Accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had taſted of it, and taken that Sacrament of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation to be true to one another, he ſwore them all to Secrecy, and then participated his Intentions, and then conſulted for the moſt proper time and means for the execution of them; but when all their black and horrid Deſigns, which they had formed againſt their Country, Laws, and Magiſtrates, were ripe for to be put in Action, and a Day appointed for the ſame, (even a time prefixt in the Month of <hi>February,</hi> as the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian tells us) their Plot was diſcovered to the Conſul, by one of their own Party, and the City ſaved, and his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42478:13"/>Life, with the Lives of the Patricians, and the whole Order of Senators, and their Liberties preſerved. Thus God to ſhew how eaſily he can baffle all the moſt cunning contrivances of the wiſeſt <hi>Achitophels,</hi> let's them go on, without ſeeming to take the leaſt notice of them: he ſuffers them to Pride, and boaſt themſelves in the happy inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their bloudy Project, and of the fitneſs and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the place for the Execution of it; he lets them go on to fill up the meaſure of their Iniquity, and then on a ſuddain when they think they have their Prey, ſo ſafe in the compaſs of their Net, that he cannot eſcape them, and that nothing can intervene to fruſtrate their expectation; Behold a Bird of the Air, a Meſſage from Heaven ſent by God into the Heart of one of their own Tribe, which prompts him to a Diſcovery, carries the Tidings, <hi>and that which hath wings tells the matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now what can we think of a Religion, if we may call it one; which Authorizes, Allows, and Commands the acting ſuch barbarous Villanies, for promoting the Intereſt of the <hi>Roman Catholick Faith,</hi> as it is by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves incongruouſly, and abſurdly called, and the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Nation back again to that Spiritual Thraldom and Captivity, out of which God had wonderfully deliver'd it, which even the worſt of Heathens would have been aſham'd to own, or in the leaſt to countenance; to the great ſcandal and reproach of our moſt Holy, Pure, and peaceable <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Profeſſion, which ſuffers much in its Credit, and Reputation, by ſuch pernicious Doctrines as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teaches, and preſcribes to thoſe of her Communion; under the colour and pretended Authority of Religion, they contrive with the greateſt Sacredneſs that can be, the moſt bloudy and inhuman Murthers, and Treaſons imaginable; making even the Holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, the Bond of their wicked Confederacies, and Combinations; both their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42478:14"/>Obligation to commit their execrable Villanies; and their Tye not to confeſs it, if it may tend to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and diſcerdit of their Holy Mother Church; when it is done. Now what Security and Guard can Mankind have againſt ſuch as have no regard for whatever they ſay, do, or ſwear, when the Cauſe which they have eſpous'd is concern'd; or when their Lives, Fortunes, or Reputations are called in queſtion: Who can but deteſt and abominate ſuch cruel and Faithleſs Principles as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all Morality, and good Nature, and which incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their Proſelytes to Murder Princes in cold Blood, and to do the Devil's work, who was a Murderer from the beginning in God's name, under the mask and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of doing him good Service. They conſecrate Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with Exorciſms, and Holy Water, for a more ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Invaſion; and that they may the more deeply, and effectually take the Dye of Proteſtant Blood, they Hallow Daggers and Piſtols with all the dire Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, of their formal, and ſoppiſh Superſtition, that they may enter the ſooner, and pierce the further into the Hearts of Gods Vicegerents. But God be praiſed, who hath defeated all their pernicious Counſels, who hath diſcovered all their deep-laid Deſigns, who hath turned back all their vaſt Preparations with ſhame, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and hath made that proud inſulting Monarch, who by theſe vile Arts, and unchriſtian, unmanly, as well as unkingly practices thought to have over-run us, and our moſt Holy Religion, a ſcorn, and a by-word, and an object of Contempt, and Reproach to all Chriſtendom. Though Satan and his Adherents ſate in full Conſult for the ruin of our Religion, and the Chief Head under Chriſt of it; yet the everlaſting Counſellor who always adviſes the beſt for his choſen, hath infatuated all their Deſigns, and hath brought that untimely Fate which they intended to others, upon their own Heads: this,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42478:14"/>God hath done for us, and it ought to be marvelous in our Eyes; That God who hath aſſured, that he will make all things conſpire, and make for the Good of thoſe who love him, and put their Truſt in him: who makes even the wrath of Man to praiſe him, and whoſe fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he can, when he pleaſes, reſtrain, and make their moſt wicked Conſpiracies, inſtrumental to their future Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Preſervation. A Tree ſhaken by the Wind, and whoſe Roots are looſened thereby within the ground, thrives the better, ſettles the faſter, and bears the more Fruit when the Storm is over: and this Government, whoſe Foundations ſeemed to be ſhaken by the violence of thoſe furious attempts, which have been made by the Prince of the Air to overthrow them, ſhall be the ſtronger and more firm for thoſe vain and empty blaſts which theſe bold Conſpirators have rais'd againſt it. It hath cut off ſome of the rotten and unſound Members already, and I hope will either hinder many from being infected with the ſame Contagion, or cure them if they have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready tainted with it. It hath united and confirmed the Hearts, and Affections of all Good Men, and made them unanimous in their Reſolutions of defending the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Perſon of their valiant Leader; and of taking new, and more effectual Methods (with ſubmiſſion ſtill to, and reliance on God's Providence, which hath hitherto watched over him, and us) for the ſecuring both Him, and our Religion, which through him was aimed at from the like dangers for the time to come. It will, and ought to make us the more watchful. and to have a ſtricter Eye over thoſe whom we now find, to be, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Character that <hi>St. Paul</hi> gives Firſt <hi>Chap.</hi> to the <hi>Romans, of thoſe whom God had given up to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Mind, to be filled with all manner of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs. and Maliciouſneſs, to be full of Envy, Murder, Debate, and Deceit, to be inventers of Evil things, Covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42478:15"/>without Natural Affection, Implacable, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful:</hi> whom no Kindneſs can oblige; but are ſtill ſtudying, and plotting to diſturb the Peace, and quiet of our <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all this, it will in all Humane Probability, have that good Influence and Operation upon a Party within our ſelves, as to open their Eyes, and to convince their Judgments, and to make them own that Duty and Allegiance, which they have ſo long neglected and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to pay; when they cannot but ſee before their Faces the Baſe, Unworthy, and inhumane Practices that have been uſed by the Papiſts, <hi>(Permiſſu &amp; Juſſu Superiorum)</hi> and by ſome among themſelves to bring about their Wicked Deſigns; and when they muſt, if they have the leaſt grain of Senſe left, acknowledge, that if what they have ſo paſſionately wiſh'd and ſtrove for, had for our Sins, been accompliſh'd by a French Power, which I hope now they will no longer deny, that they themſelves muſt have fallen a Sacrifice among the reſt to their beſotted Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottry, unleſs they would abjure that Religion which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto they ſeem ſo Zealouſly to profeſs, and to fall down before the Golden Idol of <hi>Rome.</hi> Surely they will be aſham'd to herd with the Papiſts for the time to come; ſeeing as their Principles lead them to it, ſo now they are actually detected and convicted, by Plain and Undeniable Evidence, of the moſt Barbarous and Ungenerous Attempt that almoſt was ever made, againſt the Life of a Prince, by ſecret Treachery and Ambuſhment, who hath ſo Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Bravely expoſed his Perſon to the moſt imminent Dangers upon all Occaſions, not only for the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Rights and Liberties of his Subjects, which, but for him, under GOD, had long ſince been ſwallow'd up by that great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who ſpares nothing that comes within his reach and graſp; but alſo for the recovery of the Rights and Poſſeſſions of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42478:15"/>moſt of the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> which have been invaded, and encroach'd on by the common Diſturber of the Peace, and Welfare of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>O how happy ſhould we be, if all our Diviſions and Differences were compoſed among us; then ſhould all our Enemies, either Abroad or at Home, be diſcouraged to make any more attempts againſt us; then ſhould our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion flouriſh, and the Proſperity of the Nation be firmly eſtabliſh'd among us! Let us therefore make that right uſe of GOD's Mercy thus ſignally and viſibly conferr'd upon us, by the Diſcovery of that Deteſtable Conſpiracy againſt His Majeſty's Royal Perſon and Government, as to lay aſide all diſtinctions, and frivolous Diſputes about Words more than Realities, and bear a Dutiful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrain'd Allegeance to the beſt of Princes, who thinks nothing too hazardous to undertake, nothing too painful to undergo to procure the Happineſs of his People, and the Security of their Religion.</p>
            <p>And as we have praiſed God this Morning in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Form of Thankſgiving, compoſed by his Order, for the great and ſignal Deliverance of his Perſon and Government, from all the Wicked Deſigns that were laid againſt both, ſo let us ſhew the ſincerity of our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs unto God by our conformity to his Laws, and by yielding a cheerful Obedience to the Commands of his Vice-Gerent, for whoſe ſafety he hath ſo graciouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As we have joyntly ſet our hands in token of our readineſs to imploy our whole Strength, and to uſe our utmoſt Endeavours to aſſiſt for the Defence of his Royal Perſon, and ſupport of his Government, and to bring to condign Puniſhment thoſe who ſhall offer any violence to the one, or diſturbance to the other; ſo let us now with one accord lift up our Hearts and our Voices, and aſſociate our ſelves this Day, to preſent our humble
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42478:16"/>Addreſs to the Divine Majeſty of Heaven, in behalf of our Dear and Dread Sovereign, King <hi>WILLIAM;</hi> that he may be long the Care and Darling of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and the Joy, Comfort, and Safe guard of theſe, and all other his Realms and Dominions whatſoever. He hath long, O Lord, abode in the heat of the Battel, under the cooling and refreſhing Shadow of thy gracious and protecting Providence; thou didſt cover him with thy large and capacious Wings, from the Bullets that flew about him; and now thou haſt quaſh'd all thoſe Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night-Plots and Conſpiracies that were hatch'd in the depth of Hell, and they are by thy goodneſs diſcover'd, and come to nothing. O contime thy loving kindneſs unto him, becauſe he hath known thy Name, and when he calls upon thee, do thou anſwer him. Let thy Truth and Mercy be ſtill his Shield and Buckler; Let him take to himſelf the Jealouſie for thine Honour for compleat Armour, and let him put on Righteouſneſs for a Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, and true Judgment inſtead of an Helmet: Let thy Hand, O GOD, hold him faſt, and thy hand ſtrengthen him: Hide him from the Secret Counſels of the Wicked, and from the Inſurrection of Evil-Doers, who encourage themſelves in Miſchief, that they may ſuddenly ſhoot at him that is perfect, and commune among themſelves how they may lay ſnares, and ſay, that no Man ſhall ſee them: But do thou, O Lord, ſuddenly ſhoot at them with a ſwift Arrow, that they may be wounded: Yea, let their own Tongues make them fall, that whoſo ſeeth them may laugh them to ſcorn, and that all Men may ſay, <hi>This hath the Lord done, for they ſhall perceive that it is thy Work; then ſhall the Righteous rejoyce, and put their Truſt in thee, and all they that are true of heart ſhall be glad.</hi> And that he may be a long Bleſſing to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do Thou continue to deliver him from the Evil Man, and preſerve him from the Wicked Man, who imagines
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42478:16"/>Miſchief in his Heart, and ſtirrs up ſtrife all the Day long; Keep him from the hands of the Ungodly, who had purpoſed to overthrow his Goings: Keep him from the Snares they have laid for him, and from the Traps of the Wicked-doers; Let the Ungodly fall in their own Nets together, and let him ever eſcape them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grant this, and whatever elſe we have prayed for, in much mercy to us and this Sinful Nation, for thy Dear Son</hi> Jeſus Chriſt's <hi>ſake, to whom, with thy ſelf, and Holy Spirit, be aſcribed all Honour and Glory, World without end,</hi> Amen</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42478:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42478:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
